<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideSidebarsInfo">
    <title>
      Info Sidebar
    </title>
    <para>
      The Info Sidebar shows various information about the image and can also be used for metadata editing. It consists of panes. Left-clicking on the pane title expands or collapses the pane. Right-clicking on the pane title or on empty space opens a context menu allowing you to add and remove panes, or move them up and down.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Panes"><title>
      Panes
    </title>
    <para/><section id="Histogram"><title>
      Histogram
    </title>
    <para>
      Right-click to configure
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Textpanes-TitleComment"><title>
      Text panes - Title, Comment
    </title>
    <para>
      The text is written to Xmp.dc.title and Xmp.dc.description. It can be changed in the configuration file.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Keywords"><title>
      Keywords
    </title>
    <para>
      FIXME: put <ulink url="/wiki/keywords">keywords?</ulink> here The text is written to Xmp.dc.subject. It can be changed in the configuration file.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Listpanes-ExifFileinfoCopyrightLocationandGPS"><title>
      List panes - Exif, File info, Copyright, Location and GPS
    </title>
    <para>
      The metadata tags are sorted into these main groups - Exif, File info, Copyright, Location and GPS, but it is just a matter of configuration. The item titles support drag and drop and can be dragged freely among these panes, it is also possible to drag new items from Advanced Exif window Right-clicking on an item opens the context menu
    </para>
    <para>
      Add entry
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Key
      </term><listitem><para>
        Exiv2 or Geeqie (formatted...) key FIXME: list of formatted... tags.
      </para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Title
      </term><listitem><para>
        Title that is shown.
      </para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Show only if set
      </term><listitem><para>
        Show only if the tag exists in the file.
      </para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Editable
      </term><listitem><para>
        Displays the value as editable.
      </para></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Note: Geeqie internally converts Exif and IPTC metadata to XMP on read and back on write, thus any changes made to Exif and IPTC here will be lost on write. Edit the corresponding XMP instead. An exception are Makernote tags which don't have an equivalent in XMP, but there is another limitation in that Makernote can't be written to an external file (sidecar or Geeqie private file).
    </para>
    <para>
      Show hidden
    </para>
    <blockquote>
      <para>
        Shows all entries regardless of "Show only if set".
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    <para/></section><section id="GPSMap"><title>
      GPS Map
    </title>
    <para>
      Geeqie must be built with libchamplain.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section></section>
