<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideOtherWindowsImageProperties">
    <title>
      Image Properties Window
    </title>
    <para>
      The image properties window is a dialog that displays various information about a file.
    </para>
    <para>
      To display a properties window for a an image select Properties from it's context menu, in most windows pressing Ctrl + P will display the properties of the selected images or files.
    </para>
    <para>
      The properties window contains a scaled down image of the file and information about the file under several tabs. If the window contains more than one file, they can be navigated by activating the left and right arrow buttons, or by clicking the primary and middle mouse buttons on the image preview.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Imagepreview"><title>
      Image preview
    </title>
    <para>
      This displays the contents of the active file. When the window contains more than one file, they can be navigated with the primary and middle mouse buttons. The image display is also a drag source for drag and drop, start the drag operation by pressing the middle mouse button and dragging the file to the desired target.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Generaltab"><title>
      General tab
    </title>
    <para>
      This displays information about the active file. It includes:
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        File attributes
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Modification date and time, size, owner, group, and permissions.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Image attributes
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Dimensions, uncompressed size, file or mime type, and existence of an alpha channel.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Compress ratio
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      The percentage of file size compared to the size of the image when decoded into memory.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Keywordstab"><title>
      Keywords tab
    </title>
    <para>
      The keywords tab contains the same information that is in the Keywords sidebar, please refer to the <link linkend="GuideSidebarsKeywords">Keywords Sidebar?</link> page for details.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="EXIFtab"><title>
      EXIF tab
    </title>
    <para>
      The EXIF tab contains the same information that is in the EXIF sidebar, please refer to the <link linkend="GuideSidebarsExif">EXIF Sidebar?</link> page for details.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section>
