<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideOptionsBehavior">
    <title>
      Advanced Behavior Options
    </title>
    <para>
      This section describes the options presented under the Behavior Tab of the preferences dialog.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Delete"><title>
      Delete
    </title>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Confirm file delete
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Prompts for confirmation before deleting files.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Enable Delete key
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Disable this to disassociate the delete file function from the Delete key. This option does not effect the Ctrl + D key sequence. May be useful in combination with “confirm file delete”, above, disabled so that accidentally hitting a single key will not result in deleted files.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Safe Delete
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Moves deleted files to a temporary folder, for easy retrieval of deleted files. Files in the temporary folder are retained until the maximum size is reached, at which point deleting additional files will result in the removal of the oldest files to reclaim the space needed for the new files.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note: Files moved to the Safe Delete folder are prefixed with a six digit number in the format: <literal>nnnnnn_FILENAME</literal><?db2html element="br"?>
      This is used by the delete feature to distinguish which files to remove first when clearing space for new files.<?db2html element="br"?>
      The digit counter increments with each deleted file.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Folder
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      The location of the folder used by the Safe Delete feature.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Maximum size
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      The size to use for the Safe Delete folder, in megabytes. Note that setting this value to 0 (zero) will disable any limit.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Clear button
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Removes all files contained in the Safe Delete folder.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        View button
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Changes the Geeqie main window to display the contents of the Safe Delete folder.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Behavior"><title>
      Behavior
    </title>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Rectangular selection in icon view
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Enable this to change the selection method used when selecting multiple items in an icon view.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Descend folders in tree view
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      This will allow Geeqie to read sub folder content to determine if it should display expander indicators in the folder tree view.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note: Disable this if Geeqie wakes up auto mounted network shares, or takes too long to initially display the folder view.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Show date in directories list view
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Enable this to display directory modification date along its name in the list view
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        In place renaming
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      When renaming a single file, this will allow the rename entry to appear directly over the original filename.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Show "Copy path" menu item
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Enable this option to show a "Copy path" menu item in applicable menus.
    </para>
    <para>
      This allows to copy path to files or directories to the clipboard, names are enclosed with double quotes and separated by space.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Open recent list maximum size
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      This is the number of entries saved in the recent open file list.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Drag'n drop icon size
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      This is the width and height of the icon generated from image and displayed when doing drap'n drop actions. High resolution screens may require to increase this number.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Navigation"><title>
      Navigation
    </title>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Progressive keyboard scrolling
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      This will cause image panning speed to gradually accelerate when holding down the keyboard arrows.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Mouse wheel scrolls image
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      The default is for the mouse wheel to change the image, and to scroll the image when Shift is used in combination with the wheel. Enabling this swaps the behavior so that operating the wheel will scroll the image, and holding down Shift will change the image.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Home button path
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      This defines the path to use for the "Home" button in the main window. By default or when this field is empty, this is the user's directory.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Use current
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Pressing this button will set the Home button path to the current open directory.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Miscellaneous"><title>
      Miscellaneous
    </title>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Custom similarity threshold
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      This setting is used by the compare method “similarity (custom)”, located in the Find Duplicates window.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Debugging"><title>
      Debugging
    </title>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Debug level
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      This defines the verbosity of debug info sent to console and log window (0 disables the debug output).
    </para>
  <para/></section></section>
