<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideImagePresentationSlideshow">
    <title>
      Slide Show
    </title>
    <para>
      The image pane can be set to automatically change the displayed image after a period of time, in Geeqie this is referred to as a slide show.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Startingaslideshow"><title>
      Starting a slide show
    </title>
    <para>
      A slide show can be started in a number of ways:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>From the menu bar - open the <emphasis role="strong">View</emphasis> menu and select <emphasis role="strong">Toggle slide show</emphasis> to toggle the slide show on or off .
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>From the keyboard - press the S key to toggle the slide show on or off.
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>From a context menu - right click an image pane, and select <emphasis role="strong">Start slide show</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="strong">Stop slide show</emphasis>; the text will change depending on the state of the current slide show.
      </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    <para/></section><section id="Stoppingaslideshow"><title>
      Stopping a slide show
    </title>
    <para>
      An active slide show can be stopped by using the same functions available to start one, as they work like a toggle switch. If slide show repeat is not enabled in the <link linkend="GuideOptionsGeneral">options dialog</link>, the slide show will stop when the last image in the sequence is displayed.
    </para>
    <para>
      Any action that changes the image pane to a new image will stop the active slide show, with the exception of the methods discussed in [<ulink url="/wiki#navigation">Slide show sequence navigation</ulink>].
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Slideshowstatus"><title>
      Slide show status
    </title>
    <para>
      The main window <link linkend="GuideMainWindowStatusBar">status bar</link> can be used to determine when a slide show is active, <emphasis role="strong">Slide show</emphasis> will be displayed next to the file count field. An individual <link linkend="GuideOtherWindowsImageWindow">Image Window</link> can also display a slide show, however the status will not be immediately visible. To determine the slide show status in an image window, open a context menu by right clicking or using the menu key, the slide show menu item will reflect the slide show status; if <emphasis role="strong">Start slide show</emphasis> is displayed, no slide show is active, conversely if <emphasis role="strong">Stop slide show</emphasis> is displayed a slide show is active.
    </para>
    <para>
      When a Slide show is paused, the main window status bar will display <emphasis role="strong">Paused</emphasis> instead of <emphasis role="strong">Slide show</emphasis>. Likewise, the image context menu will display <emphasis role="strong">Pause slide show</emphasis> or <emphasis role="strong">Continue slide show</emphasis>, depending on the current state.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Pausingaslideshow"><title>
      Pausing a slide show
    </title>
    <para>
      An active slide show can be paused in two ways:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>From the keyboard - press the P key while a slide show is active.
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>From a context menu - right click the image pane displaying the slide show, and select <emphasis role="strong">Pause slide show</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="strong">Continue slide show</emphasis> depending on the current slide show state.
      </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    <para/></section><section id="Selectingtheimagestoincludeinaslideshow"><title>
      Selecting the images to include in a slide show
    </title>
    <para>
      When a single image is selected, all images in the current folder are included in the slide show. The sequence will begin with the current image; however if random slide shows are enabled, the sequence will begin with a random image from the list.
    </para>
    <para>
      To only include some images in a slide show, use multiple selection to select the images to include before starting the slide show.
    </para>
    <para>
      An image collection can be used as the list of images, to do this drag an image from a collection window onto the image pane. Starting a slide show will then include the images from that collection.
    </para>
    <para>
      So far, the methods described are for slide shows in a main window, in an <link linkend="GuideOtherWindowsImageWindow">Image Window</link>, the slide show will use all images referenced by that window.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Recursiveslideshow"><title>
      Recursive slide show
    </title>
    <para>
      In the main window, a recursive slide show can be started from a folder's context menu; the folder's right click menu will include two slide show options:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>Slide show: This will start a slide show that includes all images in the selected folder.
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Slide show recursive: The slide show will include all images in the selected folder, and all images in the folders that are contained within the selected folder.
      </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    <para/></section><section id="Slideshowsequencenavigation"><title>
      Slide show sequence navigation
    </title>
    <para>
      When a slide show is active, functions that normally change the image forward and backward can be used to step through those contained in the slide show.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Configuringaslideshow"><title>
      Configuring a slide show
    </title>
    <para>
      The options that control the behavior of slide shows are located on the <link linkend="GuideOptionsGeneral">General tab</link> of the options dialog.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Display time
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      The delay between each image in the slide show can be adjusted with the Delay before image change option.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Repeat
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      This will cause the slide show to loop indefinitely, it will continue with the first image after displaying the last image in the slide show list.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Random
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      This will display images randomly selected from the slide show list. Each image from the slide show list will be displayed once. When Repeat is also enabled, the random sequence is changed after each complete cycle of the images.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section>
