<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideOptionsFiltering">
    <title>
      Filtering Options
    </title>
    <para>
      This section describes the options presented under the Filtering Tab of the preferences dialog.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Filters"><title>
      Filters
    </title>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Show hidden files or folders
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Enables the display of hidden files and folders, also known as dot files.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Show dot directory
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Enables the display of the current directory as a dot in the directories views. It may be useful for some drag'n'drop operations.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Case sensitive sort
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Files and folders are sorted such that upper case letters occur before lower case letters.
    </para>
    <para>
      Enabled result: A, B, C, a, b, c<?db2html element="br"?>
      Disabled result: A, a, B, b, C, c
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Disable file filtering
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Enable this to allow Geeqie to list all files, even those that do not contain images.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Groupingsidecarextensions"><title>
      Grouping sidecar extensions
    </title>
    <para>
      This field defines which extensions will lead to file grouping. Each extension should be separated by a semi-colon and should include the starting dot. It is possible to use wildcards: <literal>%image</literal> expands to list of all files in class image, <literal>%raw</literal> expands to raw files and <literal>%meta</literal> expands to metadata files (see the file class below).
    </para>
    <para>
      Grouped files will appear as one in file views. The group is represented by the first existing extension from the list. For example, it is useful when browsing directories containing two files for the same image (as raw+jpeg files generated by some cameras).
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Filetypes"><title>
      File types
    </title>
    <para>
      This list contains the image formats that are understood by Geeqie. To disable a specific file type from being displayed, uncheck it's corresponding checkbox. Filters can be edited by first selecting the line containing the item to be changed, then clicking the filter or description field, making any changes, then pressing Enter; press Escape to cancel an active edit. The format for the filter field is a semicolon (;) seperated list of extensions, extensions must include the period (.).
    </para>
    <para>
      Note: Unlike all other options in the dialog, filter list changes are applied immediately.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Add button
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Adds a new blank line to the filter list, change the parameters to match the desired file type.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Remove button
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Removes the selected line from the filter list.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Defaults button
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      Resets the filter list to the default values, discarding any customizations made by the user.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section>
