<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideMainWindowNavigation">
    <title>
      Navigation
    </title>
    <para/><section id="Movingaroundinthefilesystem"><title>
      Moving around in the file system
    </title>
    <para>
      To select the folder containing the desired images for display, change to the image's folder using the folder view. Single clicking a folder with the primary mouse button will change the main window to display that folder's contents. When the folder view is displayed as a list, use the folder named “..” to change to the parent folder (the parent folder is the folder that contains the current folder).
    </para>
    <para>
      To select a folder with the keyboard, move the focus to the desired folder and press the <ulink url="/wiki/SpaceBar">SpaceBar?</ulink> or Enter key.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Movingaroundwithinafolder"><title>
      Moving around within a folder
    </title>
    <para>
      After selecting the desired folder as above, the desired image can be viewed by selecting it from the file list. To select a file for display single click it with the primary mouse button.
    </para>
    <para>
      To select a file with the keyboard, move the focus to the desired file. As you move the focus within the file list the image display will update to match the highlighted file.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Goinghome"><title>
      Going home
    </title>
    <para>
      To change to your home folder, click the Home button in the tool bar. Home folder can be set in window preferences.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Directpathentry"><title>
      Direct path entry
    </title>
    <para>
      The current path is displayed in an entry field above the folder list. A folder or file can be typed into the entry to quickly change to a desired location or image, the main window will update after pressing the Enter key. Tab completion is also available in the path entry.
    </para>
    <para>
      Next to the path entry is a button with a down arrow, clicking this will display a drop down list containing the most recent locations viewed. The list is ordered such that the most recent location is at the top. Selecting a location from the drop down list will change the window to display the location.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Steppingthroughimagessequentially"><title>
      Stepping through images sequentially
    </title>
    <para>
      To change the displayed image to next or previous one within the same folder, use the respective <ulink url="/wiki/PageDown">PageDown?</ulink> and <ulink url="/wiki/PageUp">PageUp?</ulink> keys. The mouse can also be used to change the image by clicking the image display with the respective primary and middle buttons.
    </para>
    <para>
      To change to beginning or end of the image list, use the respective Home or End keys.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section>
