<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideImageManagementExternalEditing"><title/>
    <para/><section id="ExternalEditing"><title>
      External Editing
    </title>
    <para>
      Geeqie provides the ability to execute commands, such as running an image editor on a selected image. In Geeqie these are called the external editing commands.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="ExternalEditors"><title>
      External Editors
    </title>
    <para>
      External editors can do anything from running simple operations like symlink to fully featured programs like gimp.
    </para>
    <para>
      Geeqie looks for standard desktop files.
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://standards.freedesktop.org/desktop-entry-spec/">http://standards.freedesktop.org/desktop-entry-spec/</ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://standards.freedesktop.org/menu-spec/">http://standards.freedesktop.org/menu-spec/</ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
      It is also possible to add Geeqie-specific editors with the <link linkend="GuideEditorsConfig">Editor configuration dialog?</link>
    </para>
    <para>
      Editors appear in menu Edit / External Editors, unless specified otherwise in the desktop file.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Resultdialog"><title>
      Result dialog
    </title>
    <para>
      Commands that are set to display their output in a window will show a dialog when the command is executed.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Result dialog will display the command's text output. If the editor command will result in multiple runs of the same command for each file, you can use the Stop button to stop Geeqie from executing the command for remaining files.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once all commands have completed, or if the Stop button was pressed and the pending command has completed, you can use the Close button, or press Escape, to close the Result dialog. The Result dialog can not be closed while a command is still running.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section></section>
