<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="GuideCredits">
    <title>
      Credits
    </title>
    <para/><section id="Authors"><title>
      Authors
    </title>
    <para>
      Geeqie is maintained by The Geeqie Team (Vladimir Nadvornik, Petr Ostadal, Laurent Monin).
    </para>
    <para>
      This software is a fork of GQview project by John Ellis.
    </para>
    <para>
      The ever growing list of contributors and language translators can be found in the README file included with the latest release of the program.<?db2html element="br"?>
      The Credits can also be viewed by selecting the Credits button located in the About dialog <emphasis role="i">(open Help Menu, select About, click Credits... button)</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Copyright"><title>
      Copyright
    </title>
    <para>
      Geeqie and this accompanying documentation is copyright (c) 2008 - 2009 The Geeqie Team and (c) 2006 John Ellis.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="License"><title>
      License
    </title>
    <para>
      The Geeqie program is released under the “GNU General Public License”, the complete GNU GPL text can be found in the COPYING file included with each Geeqie release.
    </para>
    <para>
      This Geeqie documentation is released under the "[[gnu_fdl.txt GNU Free Documentation License]]".
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="LegalNotice"><title>
      Legal Notice
    </title>
    <para>
      Copyright (c) 2008 - 2009 The Geeqie Team.<?db2html element="br"?>
      Copyright (c) 2006 John Ellis.
    </para>
    <para>
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "[[gnu_fdl.txt GNU Free Documentation License]]".
    </para>
  <para/></section></chapter>
