<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideSidebarsSortManager">
    <title>
      Sort Manager Sidebar
    </title>
    <para>
      The Sort Manager sidebar provides a convenient method to quickly sort many files into a set of folders or collections.
    </para>
    <para>
      To toggle display of the Sort Manager press Ctrl + S or select “Sort manager” from the View menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      The mode of the Sort Manager is selected by the drop down list under the sidebar title. The Folder mode allows moving or copying the visible image to a folder, and the Collection mode allows adding the visible image or file selection to a collection.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Folderview"><title>
      Folder view
    </title>
    <para>
      The Sort Manager folder view consists of a vertical list for bookmarking folders, a section to select the operation to perform, and a set of buttons along the bottom.
    </para>
    <para>
      Clicking or activating an item in the list will copy, move, or link the active image's file to that location. The active image will then change to the next image.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Bookmarklist"><title>
      Bookmark list
    </title>
    <para>
      This is a list of possible folders to use as a destination for the selected operation. A context menu will appear by right clicking on an item, or pressing the menu key when the item has the focus.
    </para>
    <para>
      Folders can be added to the list by activating the Add button at the bottom of the sidebar, or dragging a folder onto the list.
    </para>
    <para>
      To edit an item select “Properties” from it's context menu. A dialog will appear allowing the Name, Path, and Icon for the item to be changed. Select OK to close the dialog and apply the changes, or Cancel to close the dialog and discard the changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      To change the order of the list, select “Move up” or “Move down” from the item's context menu. To move an item with the keyboard move the focus to that item, then press Shift + Up or Shift + Down to move the item.
    </para>
    <para>
      To remove an item from the list select “Remove” from it's context menu.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="CopyMoveandLink"><title>
      Copy, Move, and Link
    </title>
    <para>
      These are the available operations to use on the active image, they should be self explanatory.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Addbutton"><title>
      Add button
    </title>
    <para>
      Activate this button to add a folder to the bookmark list. A dialog will appear to allow selection of the folder to use for the new item.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Undobutton"><title>
      Undo button
    </title>
    <para>
      Activate this button to undo the last copy, move, or link operation. The undo function can only reverse the most recent operation.
    </para>
    <para/></section></section><section id="Collectionview"><title>
      Collection view
    </title>
    <para>
      The Sort Manager collection view consists of a vertical list of collection, a section to determine the current selection, and a set of buttons along the bottom.
    </para>
    <para>
      Clicking or activating an item in the list will add the selected image to that collection.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Collectionlist"><title>
      Collection list
    </title>
    <para>
      This is the list of collections located in the folder $HOME/.geeqie/collections. Activating a member of this list will result in the current image selection to be added to the collection. If the image already exists within the collection, it will not be added a second time.
    </para>
    <para>
      A new empty collection can be added to the list by activating the Add button at the bottom of the sidebar.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Choosingtheselectionstyle"><title>
      Choosing the selection style
    </title>
    <para>
      The images to add when activating a collection is determined by the selection style:
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Add image
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      The visible image is added to the collection.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Add selection
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      All images selected in the file list will be added to the collection.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Addbutton1"><title>
      Add button
    </title>
    <para>
      Activate this button to add a new empty collection to the visible list. A dialog will appear to allow entry of the name to use for the new collection.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Undobutton1"><title>
      Undo button
    </title>
    <para>
      Activate this button to undo the last add operation. The undo function can only reverse the most recent operation.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section></section>
