<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="GuideFaq">
    <title>
      Frequently Asked Questions
    </title>
    <para/><section id="Imageviewing"><title>
      Image viewing
    </title>
    <para/><section id="HowdoIkeepimagessmallerthanthevisibleareafromenlargingwhenthezoomissettofittowindow"><title>
      How do I keep images smaller than the visible area from enlarging when the zoom is set to “fit to window” ?
    </title>
    <para>
      In the preferences dialog, under the “Image” tab, disable “Allow enlargement of image for zoom to fit”.
    </para>
    <para/></section></section><section id="Commandline"><title>
      Command line
    </title>
    <para/><section id="HowdoIopenanimageinanexistingGeeqieapplication"><title>
      How do I open an image in an existing Geeqie application ?
    </title>
    <para>
      Use the “-r” command line option to send commands to an existing Geeqie, for a list of commands supported by the remote switch run:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
`geeqie --remote-help`
</programlisting>
    <para/></section><section id="HowdoIsettheslideshowdelaywhenstartingGeeqieinslideshowfromthecommandline"><title>
      How do I set the slide show delay when starting Geeqie in slide show from the command line ?
    </title>
    <para>
      The delay can not be set when used with the standard -s command line switch, as -s uses the delay stored in the configuration file. For this use the remote command -ss to start the slide show after setting the delay with -d, the order of the command line is important, for example a 12 second slide show delay:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
`geeqie -r -d12 -ss`
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Note that if geeqie is running prior to this command, the slide show should also be stopped prior to changing the delay:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
`geeqie -r -sS -d12 -ss`
</programlisting>
    <para/></section></section><section id="Miscellaneous"><title>
      Miscellaneous
    </title>
    <para/><section id="IwanttobeabletoeditimageswithGeeqie"><title>
      I want to be able to edit images with Geeqie
    </title>
    <para>
      Geeqie is an image <emphasis role="i">viewer</emphasis>. There is, and never will be, a plan to add editing features. I recommend gimp for image editing.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section></chapter>
