<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideMainWindowLayout">
    <title>
      Layout
    </title>
    <para>
      The main window consists of four areas, the <link linkend="GuideMainWindowFolderPane">folder pane</link>, <link linkend="GuideMainWindowFilePane">file pane</link>, <link linkend="GuideMainWindowImagePane">image pane</link>, and the <link linkend="GuideMainWindowStatusBar">status bar</link>. The status bar is always at the bottom of the window. The three remaining areas, or panes, can be arranged and sized by the user.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Selectingthelocationofeachpane"><title>
      Selecting the location of each pane
    </title>
    <para>
      The arrangement of the folder, file, and image pane is selected on the <link linkend="GuideOptionsWindow">Windows tab</link> of the Options window. There are four choices for the layout, the difference is that each has the larger pane in a different location: right, bottom, left, and top.
    </para>
    <para>
      The order in which the panes are filled is determined by the three row list located below the layout selection. The three numbered rows correspond to the three numbered regions of the selected layout, to change the order of the list drag a row to the desired location within the list. To drag a row move the mouse over the selected row, press and hold the primary mouse button, then drag the row to the desired location and release the button.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note: In the options window the file and image panes are labeled similarly, however the folder pane is labeled as tools.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Changingthesizeofapane"><title>
      Changing the size of a pane
    </title>
    <para>
      Between the panes of the main window are two dividers that can be moved with the mouse to adjust the size of each pane. Press and hold the primary button, then move the divider to the desired location and release the button.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Folderpane"><title>
      Folder pane
    </title>
    <para>
      The <link linkend="GuideMainWindowFolderPane">folder pane</link> contains the menu bar, tool bar, path entry, and folder list. The list can be set to display the sub folders of the active folder or a tree that starts with the root folder and contains all folders in the file system.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Filepane"><title>
      File pane
    </title>
    <para>
      The <link linkend="GuideMainWindowFilePane">file pane</link> lists the images contained in the active folder. The file pane can be set to display as a vertical list or an icon view.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Imagepane"><title>
      Image pane
    </title>
    <para>
      The <link linkend="GuideMainWindowImagePane">image pane</link> is where the active image is displayed.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section></section>
