<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="GuideIntroduction">
    <para>
      Legal Notice
    </para>
    <para>
      Copyright (c) 2008 - 2009 The Geeqie Team.<?db2html element="br"?>
      Copyright (c) 2004 John Ellis.
    </para>
    <para>
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "<ulink url="/wiki/gnu_fdl">GNU Free Documentation License?</ulink>".
    </para>
    <title>
      Introduction
    </title>
    <para>
      Geeqie is an image viewer that makes navigation of images easy. Images can be viewed full screen, and a slide show function allows automatic changing of the displayed image.
    </para>
    <para>
      Geeqie is an image manager, with complete copy, move, rename, and delete functions available at the press of a button. Find the right image with the search feature. Image collectors can free up space with a function that finds duplicate images.
    </para>
    <para>
      The one thing Geeqie is not, and never will be, is an image editor. However, Geeqie paired with an image editor, such as the Gimp, can be a very powerful combination.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="BasicFeatures"><title>
      Basic Features
    </title>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>Thumbnail preview
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Full screen
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Slide show
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Image Management
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Image Collections
      </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    <para/></section><section id="AdvancedFeatures"><title>
      Advanced Features
    </title>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>Image Search
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Find image duplicates based on image content
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>View and edit EXIF, IPTC and XMP data stored in images
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Simple Sort Manager to quickly sort a folder of images into other folders
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Rename images in bulk
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Add XMP keywords to images, and recall those images with the search function
      </para></listitem><listitem><para>Very Configurable
      </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    <para>
      “An application that displays images.” - This was, and still is, the primary goal of Geeqie. Over time image management features have been added, but the core purpose of Geeqie remains the same.
    </para>
  <para/></section></chapter>
