<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="GuideImageManagementRename">
    <title>
      Rename
    </title>
    <para>
      To rename a file in Geeqie press Ctrl + R, or select Rename from the File menu. Rename is also available in the context menu of all images and files.
    </para>
    <para>
      When renaming a file, a dialog will display allowing entry of the new name for the file. The dialog will be different depending on the number of files selected to be renamed. A simple dialog will appear when renaming a single file, however when renaming multiple files the dialog will include a list of the file to be renamed and additional options.
    </para>
    <para/><section id="Renamesinglefiledialog"><title>
      Rename single file dialog
    </title>
    <para>
      The dialog that appears when renaming a single file includes an image of the file, an entry to type the new name of the file, a Rename button, and a Cancel button. Type the new name into the text entry and press Enter or activate the Rename button to rename the file. Press Escape or activate the Cancel button to close the dialog and abort renaming the file.
    </para>
    <para>
      When renaming a file and the new name already exists on the file system a dialog will appear showing the renamed and existing files. To overwrite the existing file press Enter or activate the Overwrite button. Press Escape or activate the Cancel button to close the dialog abort renaming the file.
    </para>
    <para/></section><section id="Renamemultiplefilesdialog"><title>
      Rename multiple files dialog
    </title>
    <para>
      The dialog that appears when renaming multiple files includes the list of files to be renamed, a preview image of the active file, an entry to enter the new file name, an auto rename check box, a Rename button, and a Cancel button.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Manually enter new file names
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      To manually enter the new name of each file, the active file will be displayed in the image preview and it's original name will be displayed above the text entry. To rename the file type the new name and press Enter or activate the Rename button. When a file is successfully renamed it will be removed from the list and the next one will become the active file. After all files have been renamed, the dialog will close.
    </para>
    <para>
      Files do not have to be renamed in the order that they appear in the list, highlighting a name in the list will make it become the active file.
    </para>
    <para>
      When renaming a file and the new name already exists on the file system a dialog will appear showing the renamed and existing files. To overwrite the existing file press Enter or activate the Overwrite button. Press Escape or activate the Cancel button to return to the original rename dialog, the file that prompted the overwrite dialog will remain active.
    </para>
    <variablelist><varlistentry><term>
        Automatic renaming of multiple files
      </term><listitem><para/></listitem></varlistentry></variablelist>
    <para>
      To automatically rename the files in the list, enable the Auto rename check box. The dialog will change to batch mode for numerical naming of files.
    </para>
    <para>
      The file name list will change to include a preview column that will show the resulting name of each file. The text entry will change to three entries; the first represents the text that appears in the new names before the number, the second will be the start number to use when incrementing the file number, and the third represents the text to append to the name after the number. The end text should include the file name extension, therefore batch renaming multiple types of files (those with different extensions) all at once is not recommended.
    </para>
    <para>
      The padding number can be used to change the minimum length of characters to use for the number portion of the new name. When the file number results in fewer characters than the padding size, the result will be padded with leading zeros to fill the remaining space. For example if padding size is 3, a file with the number 24 will appear in the file name as “024”.
    </para>
    <para>
      The order of the file list can be changed by dragging a name to the desired location within the list. The preview column will update to reflect the new order.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the preview of new names is satisfactory, press Enter or activate the Rename button to rename the files to match the name in the preview column. Press Escape or activate the Cancel button to close the dialog and abort the rename operation.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the resulting new names match any existing files, a warning dialog will notify you. The rename dialog will remain so that you can select a different set of names.
    </para>
  <para/></section></section>
