<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter xml:id="config">
	<title>PKCS#11 Configuration</title>

	<section id="config-introduction">
		<title>Consistent configuration</title>

		<para>In order for multiple applications on the user's desktop to use
			PKCS#11 modules in a consistent manner, there must be a configuration
			or registry to specify which modules to load and how to use them. The
			PKCS#11 specification does not specify such a configuration standard.
		</para>

		<para>Because of the multi-library module initialization problem, use of
			PKCS#11 modules must be coordinated within an application. p11-kit
			provides that coordination. Since coordination is required, it follows
			that p11-kit can also implement a consistent module configuration.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="config-format">
		<title>File format</title>

		<para>A complete configuration consists of several files. These files are
		text files. Since <literal>p11-kit</literal> is built to be used in all
		sorts of environments and at very low levels of the software stack, we
		cannot make use of high level configuration APIs that you may find on a
		modern desktop.</para>

		<para>Each setting in the config file is specified consists of a name and
		a value. The name is a simple string consisting of characters and dashes.
		The name consists of alpha numeric characters, dot, hyphen and
		underscore.</para>

		<para>The value is specified after the name on the same line, separated
		from it by a <literal>:</literal> (colon). White space between the
		name and value is ignored.</para>

		<para>Blank lines are ignored. White space at the beginning or end of
		lines is stripped. Lines that begin with a <literal>#</literal> character
		are ignored as comments. Comments are not recognized when they come after
		a value on a line.</para>

		<para>A fictitious sample configuration file might look like:</para>

		<programlisting>
	name:value
	# Here is a comment

	setting.2: A long value with text.
	x-custom : text</programlisting>

	</section>

	<section id="config-module">
		<title>Module Configuration</title>

		<para>Each configured PKCS#11 module has its own config file. The
		location(s) of these files are described below. Most importantly each
		config file specifies the location of the PKCS#11 module to load. Each
		module config file has the following fields:</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>module:</term>
				<listitem><para>The absolute path to the PKCS#11 module to load.
				This should include an extension like <literal>.so</literal></para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>Other fields may be present, but it is recommended that field names
		that are not specified in this document start with a <literal>x-</literal>
		prefix.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="config-global">
		<title>Global Configuration</title>

		<para>A global configuration is also present. This file contains settings
		that are not related to a single PKCS#11 module. The location(s) of the
		global configuration are described below. The global configuration file
		can contain the following fields:</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>user-config:</term>
				<listitem><para>This will be equal to one of the following values:
				<literal>none</literal>, <literal>merge</literal>,
				<literal>only</literal>.</para></listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<para>Other fields may be present, but it is recommended that field names
		that are not specified in this document start with a <literal>x-</literal>
		prefix.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="config-locations">
		<title>Configuration Files</title>

		<para>Each configured PKCS#11 module is has its own config file. These
		files are placed in a directory. In addition a global config file exists.
		There is a system configuration consisting of the various module config
		files and a file for global configuration. Optionally each user can provide
		additional configuration or override the system configuration.</para>

		<para>The system global configuration file is in
		<literal>/etc/pkcs11/pkcs11.conf</literal> and the user global
		configuration file is in <literal>~/.pkcs11/pkcs11.conf</literal> in the
		user's home directory.</para>

		<para>
			The module config files are located in the
			<literal>/etc/pkcs11/modules</literal> directory, with one configuration
			file per module. In addition the <literal>~/.pkcs11/modules</literal>
			directory can be used for modules installed by the user.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
